Thief. Warrior. Gladiator. King.
Conan the Barbarian is a adventure, fantasy,
action film directed by John Milius.
A horde of rampaging warriors massacre the parents of young Conan and
enslave the young child for years on The Wheel of Pain.
As the sole survivor of the childhood massacre, Conan is released
from slavery and taught the ancient arts of fighting.
Transforming himself into a killing machine, Conan travels into the wilderness to seek
vengeance on Thulsa Doom, the man responsible for killing his family.
In the wilderness, Conan takes up with the thieves Valeria and Subotai.
The group comes upon King Osric, who wants the trio of warriors to help
rescue his daughter who has joined Doom in the hills.
Conan, played by Arnold Schwarzenegger.
Thulsa Doom, played by James Earl Jones.
King Osric, played by Max von Sydow.
Valeria, played by Sandahl Bergman.
Rexor, played by Ben Davidson.
The Witch, played by Cassandra Gava.
Conan the Barbarian is a 1982 American sword-and-sorcery film directed by
John Milius from a screenplay he co-wrote with Oliver Stone.
Based on Robert E.
Howard's Conan, the epic film stars Arnold Schwarzenegger and James Earl Jones, and tells the story of a barbarian warrior named Conan
(Schwarzenegger) who seeks to avenge his parents' deaths at the hands of Thulsa Doom (Jones), the leader of a snake cult.
Ideas for a Conan film were proposed as early as
1970; executive producer Edward R.
Pressman and associate producer Edward Summer began a
concerted effort to get the film made in 1975.
It took them two years to obtain the film rights, after which they recruited
Schwarzenegger for the lead role and Stone to draft a script.
Pressman lacked capital for the endeavor.
In 1979, after having his proposals for investments rejected by the major studios, he sold
the project to Dino De Laurentiis; his daughter Raffaella produced the film.
Milius was appointed as director and he rewrote Stone's script.
The final screenplay integrated elements from various Howard stories, as well
as the Japanese films Seven Samurai (1954) and Kwaidan (1965).
Filming took place in Spain over five months in the regions
around Madrid and the province of Almería.
The sets, designed by Ron Cobb, were based on Dark Age
cultures and Frank Frazetta's paintings of Conan.
Milius eschewed optical effects, preferring to realize his ideas
with mechanical constructs and optical illusions.
Schwarzenegger performed most of his own stunts, and two types of
sword, costing $10,000 each, were forged for his character.
The editing process took over a year, and several violent scenes were cut out.
Conan the Barbarian was distributed by Universal Pictures in the United
States and Canada and 20th Century-Fox in other territories.
It premiered on March 16, 1982, in Spain and May 14, 1982, in North America.
Upon release, the film received mixed reviews from critics and audiences alike, mainly positive for its action sequences, production design, directing,
visual style, and effects, but negatively received for its violent content and screenwriting, as well as some substandard performances.
Despite this, the film became a commercial success for its backers, grossing between $69 million
and $79 million at box offices around the world against its budget of $20 million.
The film earned Schwarzenegger worldwide recognition.
Conan the Barbarian has been frequently released on home video, the sales of which
had increased the film's gross to more than $300 million by 2007.
In the years following its release, it became a cult film, and its
success spawned a sequel, titled Conan the Destroyer (1984).
It ultimately led to the production of a 2011 reboot of the same name.
The film explores themes of based on novel or book,
gladiator, fight, magic, repayment.